A Guide to the Governor James Pleasants Executive Papers, 1822-1825
Library of Virginia
Additional significant correspondence includes the following: John Taylor accepting his appointment as senator in Congress (1822 Dec. 21); Directors of the Penitentiary re. annual reports of the operations of the Penitentiary (1822 Dec. 21); John Taylor acknowledging receipt of his credential as senator in Congress (1823 Feb, 22); William Gray, British Consul at Norfolk, re. the imprisonment of a free negro named John Jackson, a British subject from Nova Scotia (1823 March 3); A. S. Brockenbrough, University of Virginia, re. a balance against him for monies advanced to pay for certain improvements around the Capitol (1823 March 13); John Adams, Mayor of Richmond, encl. a letter & advertisement from Ezra A. Stevens concerning his lectures on astronomy (1823 May 17); G. Bomford, Ordnance Dept., re. the apportionment of arms to the several states & territories of the United States procures under the act of 1808 (1823 Aug. 22); Capt. Samuel Cary offering to raise a company of volunteers to guard the convicts (1823 Aug. 10); Jesse Williams proposing to do the brick work at the Penitentiary (1823 Aug. 12); John Brockenbrough re. a loan from the Bank of Virginia (1823 Aug. 15); James W. Steel & R. M. Gaw, Philadelphia, proposing to engrave the general map of Virginia (1823 Aug. 16); John Adams requesting arms for the use of the militia & night watch in Richmond (1823 Sept. 1); Otis Manson re. the completion of the roof of the Penitentiary (1823 Sept. 19); Thomson F. Mason accepting his appointment as commissioner to settle the western limits of the state & the dividing line between Maryland & Virginia (1823 Sept. 20); George R. Myers re. his account for labor & materials expended in the repairs of the brick work at the Penitentiary (1823 Oct. 3 & 22); Lt. Thomas J. Baird, Bellona Arsenal, re. the arrival of a portion of the arms intended by the U. S. for the State of Virginia (1823 Oct. 3); J. Brown, 2nd Auditor, re. the alteration of his office to keep off the dampness (1823 Nov. 24); J. Brown re. his bond as 2nd Auditor (1824 Feb. 9); John A. Gimball, Secretary of State of Mississippi, encl. a resolution re. the neutrality of the U. S. in the war against Spain (1824 Jan. 27); William C. Holt, Speaker of the Senate, requesting a carpet for the staircase, passage, & gallery of the Capitol (1824 Feb. 25); Peter Dupuy proposing to lease the Boring Mill at the Armory (1824 March 1); James Madison re. his appointment as visitor of the University of Virginia (1824 March 11); Way & Gideon re. the publication of the "Journals of the Old Congress" (1824 March 12); Chapman Johnson re. the state's claim against the General Government for interest on advances during the late war (1824 March 23); J. Robertson, Jr., resigning as Register of the Land Office for an appointment as Collector of Customs for the Port of Petersburg (1824 April 23); Daniel Totty requesting permission to remove a house from the public ground near the Penitentiary (1824 May 31); Chris Manch enclosing his proposal to construct a Bell Tower on the southwest corner of Capitol Square (includes drawing) (1824 June 13); John Brockenbrough encl. a resolution of the Common Council of Richmond to appoint a committee to enquire of the Commonwealth whether they are willing to relinquish the charge of Capitol Square (1824 June 16); Thomas Stanton enclosing his proposal to construct a Bell Tower on the southwest corner of Capitol Square (includes drawing) (1824 June 23); Lewis A. Tarascon re. the propriety of establishing a wagon road from the Missouri River to the Columbia River (1824 July 1); Thomson F. Mason re. the boundary line between Virginia & Maryland (1824 July 10 & 17); John Goddin regarding his proposal to construct the Bell Tower on Capitol Square (1824 July 13); William Clinton re. the duel between Gen. John C. Hunter & Thomas Hewet (1824 Nov. 21); Lt. Edgar Allan Poe & Capt. John Lisle, Richmond Junior Volunteers, re. permission to retain arms drawn from the Armory (1824 Nov. 17 & 23); George & Pleasant Winston proposing to undertake the work for repairing the Penitentiary (1824 Dec. 9); John Tyler, Chairman of a Committee of the House of Delegates, encl. a resolution appointing a committee to enquire into the expediency of reimbursing from the Treasury the whole or any part of the expenditure incurred in the reception of Gen. Lafayette at Yorktown (1824 Dec. 27); James Mitchell encl. a list of Illinois bounty lands for sale or redemption (1825 Jan. 13); Andrew Stevenson encl. a letter from Lafayette accepting the invitation of the General Assembly (1825 Jan. 14); the Committee of the Congregation of Monumental Church requesting the Public Guard to have the bell run every Sabbath to announce public worship (1825 Jan. 28); Philip P. Barbour accepting his appointment as judge of the General Court (1825 Feb. 10); John Brockenbrough, Chairman of the Committee of the Common Hall of Richmond, re. contracts for work to be done on Capitol Square (1825 Feb. 22); John Brockenbrough re. the improvement of the walks & planting on Capitol Square (1825 Feb. 24); John Adams, Mayor of Richmond, requesting the Executive to appoint commissioners to divide the city into wards (1825 March 3); J. S. Johnston, Senate Chamber, encl. resolutions in relation to the application of the funds, derived from public lands, to education & internal improvements (1825 March 4); Thomas Jefferson re. the law passed by Congress authorizing the payment to Virginia of such a portion of her claim as will cover the donation of $50,000 to the University of Virginia (1825 March 10); T. Cadwallader re. the swords made for Generals Gaines & Scott & Capt. Warrington as gifts from the state of Virginia (1825 April 5 & 20); Edward Valentine, Jr., recommending directors of the Lunatic Hospital at Staunton (1825 April 9); Claude Crozet re. his opinion of the map of Virginia created by Herman Boye (1825 April 15); Charles H. Hyde, Captain of the Fire Company lately organized in Richmond, requesting the use of the engine belonging to the state (1825 April 17); John Brockenbrough on behalf of the Commissioners of Streets in Richmond requesting permission to remove the earth between the Bell House & Bank Street and to convey the water of the spring between the Capitol & Gun House through a hydrant at Bank Street (1825 April 28); T. Mason, President of the Potomac Company, encl. proceedings of the general meeting of the proprietors of the Potomac Company (1825 May 19); William Seldon re. his bond as Register of the Land Office (1825 May 23); John Henson re. his claim for an additional allowance for covering the Lexington Arsenal (includes sketch of cupola & correspondence) (1825 May 23); James Monroe re. his message to Congress before his retirement from office (1825 June 7); George Hay re. the resolutions of the House of Delegates to present to General Lafayette copies of the Bill of Rights & other public acts (1825 Aug. 13); Levi Swain re. the completion of his work at the Capitol (1825 Oct. 4); William H. Cabell, judge of the Court of Appeals, re. smoke in the rooms prepared under the act of the General Assembly for the accommodation of the Court of Appeals & Clerk of the Court (1825 Oct. 26); and Anderson Barret re. his examination of the fireplaces in the rooms lately fitted out for the Court of Appeals (1825 Nov. 1).
Other noteworthy items include: certificates of oath for James Pleasants, Jr., as governor (1822 Dec. 17 & 1823 Dec. 17); proclamations of Governor Pleasants & Lt. Governor Peter V. Daniel offering a reward for the apprehension of escaped convicts (1823 Jan. 22; 1823 March 28; 1823 April 9; 1823 May 9 & 19; 1823 July 11; 1823 Oct. 10 & 27; 1823 Nov. 24; 1823 Dec. 5; 1824 March 17; 1824 April 30; 1824 May 15; 1824 July 16 & 22; 1824 Sept. 29; 1824 Oct. 25; 1825 Feb. 1; 1825 April 1; 1825 May 11 & 31; 1825 Sept. 28; 1825 Oct. 18); proceedings of the Board of Directors of the Penitentiary (1823 Jan. 29; 1823 March 19; 1823 April 1; 1823 May 5, 21, & 23; 1823 June 11 & 24; 1823 July 30; 1823 Sept. 11; 1823 Oct. 10; 1823 Nov. 25; 1823 Dec. 3, 10, 17, 24, & 31; 1824 Feb. 4, 11, & 28; 1824 March 24; 1824 April 9; 1824 June 2 & 9; 1824 Oct. 29; 1824 Nov. 18; 1824 Dec. 24; 1825 March 17; 1825 May 2; 1825 Aug. 5; & 1825 Dec. 6); reports of the Committee appointed by the Executive to examine the Auditor's & Treasurer's Offices (1823 March 8; 1823 Aug. 16; 1823 Nov. 14; & 1825 Jan. 7 & Nov. 12); a general account of Executive expenditures occasioned by the burning of the Penitentiary House on 8 August 1823 (1823 Nov. 28); reports of the Directors of the Penitentiary on the practicality & expense of repairing the Penitentiary (1823 Aug. 12); a contract with James Bootwright for supplying rations for Capt. Cary's Company of Militia guarding the convicts at the Penitentiary (1823 Aug. 18); a report of the Executive Committee on the Penitentiary (1823 Sept. 6); an article by James Mease, M.D., "On the Penitentiary System of Pennsylvania" (1823 Dec. 26); a resolution of Alabama that Gen. Andrew Jackson should succeed James Monroe as president (1823 Dec. 26); a bill (H.R. 252) authorizing the payment of interest due to the State of Virginia (1824 Jan. 3); resolutions of citizens of Mississippi re. the qualifications of Maj. Gen. Andrew Jackson as president, the nomination of Gen. Thomas Hinds, Dr. B. C. Barry, & Gen. James Patton, and the appointment of a committee of correspondence(1824 Feb. 9); a proclamation by Governor Pleasants re. an election to supply the vacancy in Congress occasioned by the death of William Lee Ball (1824 March 5); recommendations for Register of the Land Office (1824 April); a report of the commissioners appointed to settle the western limits of the state & the dividing line between Virginia & Maryland (1824 Nov. 1); a proclamation re. the meeting of electors for president & vice president (1824 Nov. 15); an estimate of the expenses in publishing the map of Virginia by Herman Boye (1824 Dec. 20); a report & accounts of the committee appointed by the Executive to make suitable arrangements for the reception & accommodation of General Lafayette (1825 Feb. [N.D.]); a report of the commissioners appointed to locate the Western Lunatic Asylum (1825 April 2); the appointment of the Court of Directors of the Western Lunatic Hospital (1825 April 19); the contract of John Woodson for cleaning & packing arms at the Lexington Arsenal (1825 May 6); and a proposal by the Court of Appeals to change the plan of alterations for the General Court room in the Capitol (1825 June 17).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically by date of document with pardons and undated items arranged to the rear.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1808-December 31, 1835, VOL. X, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1892.
Contents List
- James Pleasants Executive Papers
- 1822
  - December
    - 12-20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 21-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1823
  - January
    - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - February
    - 3-15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 17-28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - March
    - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 17-31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - April
    - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - May
    - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - June
    - 1-8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 9-14 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 16-20 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 21-25 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 26-30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - July
    - 1-7 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 8-18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 19-30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - August
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - September
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - October
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - November
    - 1-14 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - December
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 17-31 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pardons
    - A-F (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - G-W (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- 1824
  - January (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - February
    - 2-20 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 21-28 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - March
    - 1-12 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - April
    - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 19-30 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - May
    - 1-20 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 22-31 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - June
    - 1-9 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 10-19 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 21-27 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 28-30 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - July
    - 1-5 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 6-15 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 16-28 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 29-31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - August
    - 3-15 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - September
    - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 17-30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - October
    - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - November
    - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - December
    - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 17-30 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Pardons
    - A-L (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - M-W (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- 1825
  - January
    - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 17-31 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - February
    - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 16-30 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - March
    - 1-14 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 16-30 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - April
    - 1-9 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 11-28 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - May
    - 2-10 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 11-23 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 24-31 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - June
    - 1-10 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 11-20 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 21-30 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - July
    - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 16-30 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - August
    - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 16-30 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - September (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - October
    - 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 17-29 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - November
    - 1-12 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 14-20 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 21-26 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 27-30 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - December (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Pardons
    - B-M (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - R-W (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Oversized (Clamshell Box)
  - 1822
    - Dec. 23 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1823
    - March 4 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - April 12 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - June 21 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Aug. 22 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Nov. 14 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Nov. 28 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Dec. 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Dec. 10 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Pardons - Becks, Nicholas (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - 1824
    - March 23 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - April 22 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - April 27 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - June 12 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - July 16 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Sept. 1 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Oct. 1 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Oct. 28 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Dec. 3 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Dec. 11 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Pardons
    - Alsop, Thomas (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Joe of Pierce (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Jones, Thomas (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - 1825
    - Jan. 1 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Jan. 1 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Feb. 15 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - March 16 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - May 19 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - June 8 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - July 8 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Aug. 18 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Dec. 5 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Dec. 10 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Pardons - Dixon, George (Box 9, Folder 34)
- Oversized (Newspaper Box)
  - 1823
    - Jan. 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - March 11 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - June 14 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1824
    - Nov. 23 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1825
    - June 22 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - June 27 (Box 10, Folder 6)